Welcome to day two of week four, when we get more into leaderboards so that by the end of this, you'll
넷째 주 둘째 날입니다 순위표를 더 살펴보죠 오늘 하루가 끝날 때쯤이면 기대했던
know more than you ever wanted to know or dreamed of knowing about leaderboards and metrics and benchmarks
것보다 더 많은 걸 알게 될 겁니다 순위표, 수치 벤치마크,
and arenas and all of that.
경기장 등이요
But you'll find it incredibly useful and important as you look to understand how to pick the right LLM
하지만 이 작업은 매우 유용하고 중요합니다 작업에 적합한 LLM을 고르는 법을 이해하는
for the task at hand.
것이니까요
So the plan for today, uh, last time we talked about comparing Llms using basic attributes and using
자, 오늘의 계획은 지난 시간에 기본 특성과 벤치마크를 이용한 LM 비교를 다뤘는데요
Today you're going to look beyond the open LLM leaderboard from hugging face at other leaderboards and
오늘 여러분은 오픈 LLM의 순위표 너머를 보게 될 겁니다 다른 순위표에서 얼굴을 맞대고 인사하는
arenas that let you compare and evaluate llms.
것에서부터 비교와 평가의 무대까지 말이죠
We're also going to look at some real world use cases of llms solving commercial problems, uh, which
또한 llms의 실제 유스케이스를 통해 상업적 문제를 해결할 겁니다 여러분에게
will be hopefully, uh, insightful for you.
도움이 될 것 같군요
We'll just do that quickly, because I think everyone has exposure to so many these days, but it will
빠르게 하겠습니다 요즘은 다들 많이 접하셨겠지만 생각할
give you food for thought and it should, in summary, arm you to be able to choose the right LLM for
거리를 줄 겁니다 요약하자면 프로젝트에 맞는 LLM을 선택할 수 있도록 지원해주는
your projects.
거죠
So we're going to be doing a tour of six essential leaderboards that are available through Huggingface
그래서 6개의 필수 리더보드를 투어에 쓸 거예요 H깅페이스와 그 너머를 통해 보실
and beyond.
수 있죠
Huggingface.
포옹하는 얼굴요
For comparing Llms, the first of them is actually one that we've already seen the Huggingface OpenAI
LM을 비교해 보죠 첫 번째는 이미 봤던 H깅페이스 OpenAI 리더보드
leaderboard comparing.
비교고요
There's both the old version, but now there's the new version, which has the harder metrics.
구 버전과 새 버전이 있는데 더 어려운 측정법이죠
It's of course open source models, but it is the go to place to compare open source models.
물론 오픈 소스 모델이지만 오픈 소스 모델을 비교하기 위한 곳이죠
There is also a leaderboard called Big Code on Huggingface, which is a leaderboard that compares models
H깅페이스에 빅 코드라는 leaderboard도 있어요 코드를 생성하기 위해
specifically that are designed to generate code.
특별히 디자인된 모델들을 비교하는 거죠
And we'll be doing that looking at those examples and how it assesses models in just a second.
잠시 후 그 예시를 살펴보고 모델을 어떻게 평가하는지 살펴보죠
There is one called the LM perf board, which is another Huggingface board that talks, thinks about
LM 향수 보드라는 것이 있는데 H징페이스 보드로서
performance, uh, about both accuracy and the actual speed and cost of compute.
성능과 정확성, 실제 속도와 연산 비용을 모두 고려하죠
So this is a super important one that looks at a different dimension.
이건 다른 차원을 보는 아주 중요한 거예요
It's looking at some of the basic attributes, and it's one that again is going to become a go to resource
기본 속성을 살펴보고 있어요 여러분을 위해 리소스로 가는 것이
for you, particularly when you're thinking about inference of open source models compared to their
될 겁니다 특히 오픈 소스 모델과 폐쇄 소스 모델을 비교해 추론할 때를
closed source cousins.
생각해 보세요
And then there are some other hugging face boards.
포옹하는 얼굴 보드도 있어요
There's so much on hugging face.
포옹하는 표정에는 할 게 많아요
There are more.
더 있어요
There are specific leader boards designed for different business areas.
여러 사업 분야에 맞게 디자인된 리더 보드가 있어요
You're going to see a medical leaderboard which is designed for, uh, of course, uh, medical use
여러분이 보실 것은 의료용 리더보드입니다 의료용 사용 사례를 위해 설계된
cases.
것이죠
You're going to see leaderboards for other languages.
다른 언어에 대한 leaderboard도 볼 수 있어요
I think there's one Portuguese.
포르투갈인은 한 명이에요
I just saw that.
방금 봤어요
I'll show you.
보여드릴게요
There's a bunch of different language specific leaderboards depending on your use case.
사용 사례에 따라 다양한 언어별 leaderboard가 있어요
That might be the leaderboard that's right for you.
순위표에 잘 맞을지도 모르겠네요
Then we're going to go and look at Valheim's leaderboard.
발하임의 순위표를 보도록 하죠
You may remember we we briefly looked at this uh, early on.
기억하실지 모르겠지만 초기에 잠깐 살펴봤어요
It's a very useful resource which has a number of leaderboards, um, that include open and closed source.
여러 개의 leaderboard가 있는 아주 유용한 리소스죠 오픈소스와 폐쇄소스가 있어요
So it's one of the places where you can bring together the full family of models.
모든 모델이 한자리에 모일 수 있는 곳이죠
It also has that useful table, if you remember, that has cost, API costs and contacts window lengths.
또 유용한 테이블도 있어요 비용이요, API 비용과 연락처 창 길이
And so it's another one to add to your bookmarks because it's one of the few places which which reliably
책갈피에 추가할 만한 또 다른 장소죠 모든 정보가 한 곳에
has all of that information up to date in one place.
있는 몇 안 되는 곳이니까요
And then the last of the leaderboards that we'll look at is called Seal, which assesses various expert
마지막 순위표는 씰이라고 해요 전문가의 기술을 평가하는 거죠 순위표 세트에
skills, and they are always adding new leaderboards to to this set of leaderboards.
항상 새로운 순위표를 추가해요
So it's it is, if I may say, another one to bookmark.
그러니 책갈피로 삼을 만한 또 다른 책이죠
So your bookmarks are going to get crowded because these are great resources and I think you will thank
여러분의 책갈피가 가득 찰 거예요. 왜냐하면 좋은 리소스들이니까요. 나중에 사용해야 할 때
me when you need to use them in the future.
저에게 고마워할 거예요.
We are then also going to look at something called the Chatbot Arena, the LMS Chatbot Arena.
챗봇 아레나라는 것도 살펴볼 겁니다 LMS 챗봇 아레나죠
It is a fantastic resource.
환상적인 자원이죠
It is specifically looking at the instruct the chat use case, the ability of models to chat.
채팅 사용 지시 사례를 특히 보고 있어요 모델이 채팅하는 기능이죠
But the idea is rather than having some sort of benchmark test, it relies on human judgement to decide
하지만 이건 일종의 기준 테스트가 아니라 채팅으로 지시하는
which model is better at the kind of, uh, the, the, um, the instruction following chats.
모델에 어떤 모델이 더 적합한지 인간의 판단을 통해 결정하자는 거죠
Um, And it's just a qualitative decision by a human to decide to pick a model A or model B whilst chatting
모델 A와 B 중 하나를 선택하는 건 질적인 결정이에요 두 모델과 함께 대화하면서요
And it's a blind test in that you don't know which model is which and you have to vote without knowing.
어떤 모델이 어떤 모델인지 모르는 블라인드 테스트예요 모르는 채로 투표해야 하죠
Um, and models are given an Elo rating, which I mentioned before based on their overall, uh, um,
모델에게 Elo 점수를 주는데 앞서 언급한 대로 여러 번의 인체
how they rank overall against their, their, their peers, um, from many human tests.
실험을 통해 동료들과 비교해 종합 순위를 매겨요
So we'll see this.
이걸 보죠
We'll get to do some voting ourselves.
Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, Get, get 우리가 직접 투표를 할 거예요
And then finally we're going to look at a bunch of commercial use cases, everything from law to talent
마지막으로 상업적 유스 케이스를 살펴볼 겁니다 법과 재능,
to code to healthcare to education, seeing llms in action.
코드 의료와 교육 llms의 실태를 살펴볼 거예요
And of course, this this could be ten times more.
물론 이건 10배는 더 클 거예요
The Llms are making an impact in every business vertical you can imagine, but it's always useful to
림은 모든 비즈니스 수직에 영향을 미치고 있습니다. 하지만 몇 가지를
see a few of them and get a sense of what's out there.
보고 감을 잡는 것도 유용하죠.
So we will do all of that now.
지금 다 할 거예요
And, uh, prepare, prepare to do some bookmarking because you're going to see a lot of useful stuff
책갈피도 꽂아두시고요 유용한 걸 많이 보시거든요